so here's another question about the
five
hindrances bante I see the five
hindrances or I've been contemplating
them as ways that I try to manage my
suffering when I suffer I get angry I
seek sensual Pleasures take on projects
uhhuh pointless or not pointless
distract myself with entertainment or or
sleep or relentlessly M search for
answers to calm myself down it feels
like I'm just coexisting or learning how
to coexist with my illness rather than
curing it but if I stop managing my
suffering in these
ways what should I be doing instead what
else is there well non-management of
suffering is there but first and
foremost that's not what hindrances are
all whatever the whole thing that was
described there those are already
results of hindrances
like you don't engage with hindrances
once you get angry getting angry in the
first place is already a
hindrance so liability to to to to uh
lust liability to aversion anger
liability to restlessness or worry or
doubt that's already a hindrance those
are already signs and features of
hindrances signs and charact secondary
characteristics uh that you're not
seeing so you think the hindrance is
when you're fully engaged with with your
desires and so on no that's already like
like complete the result of the
proliferated hindrance that you that you
fully under so you have to give up the
under so you have to give up the
management so what do I do then well
there you go what do you do then
question comes up pressure to do
something comes up well that's already a
hindrance it's already going to be one
so you you discern a hindrance in
whatever comes
up so you stop doing the management
I bet your restlessness and anxiety
would increase cuz I have all this all
this daa coming up and I'm not doing
anything about it so that's that's a
pressure isn't it that's an internal
pressure that's trying to make you act
trying to get you to do trying to pick
it up take the
bait that's already the hindrance and if
you pick it
up you stepped into it right into the
track doubt doubt will come up for sure
oh but but I'm not clear about this I'm
not clear about that pressure builds up
you start seeking
Clarity out of that acting out of that
pressure because the pressure is
uncomfortable and yes it's not going to
be perfect you're bound to be doing it
to some extent but you want to be able
to like hold
on acting out of pressure is what
hinders me there is no external justification as
me there is no external justification as
to what I direct my actions for
sure uh from the worldly point of view
there there better ways of acting out of
hindrances in worse ways but
fundamentally if you're trying to be
free from hindrances they're all the
same acting out pressure means you're
hindered so that's when you start to
recognize as well okay doubt it
pressures me but it's not really about
the clarity the way it presents itself
it's about acting out of pressure it's
about getting rid of the discomfort of
the pressure so you abstain no I will
not seek for clarity and answers
for as long as this pressure does not
subside when the pressure subside I can
try and seek if truly I needed Clarity
and answers but often after the pressure
would have subsided I don't know how
long it would take maybe days you then
find out that you already knew the
answer what you were seeking supposedly
seeking for um and it was all just a
just a just a just a show just Mas just
sort of trying to um hook you bait you
into acting out of pressure and on a
pretext of like a but this is a valid
valid reason MH so that's already acting
out of hind so you have loads to do when
you stop doing the management but it
will all be on the level of uh
abstaining from doing that's rooted in
pressure Discerning that cultivating the
the those perceptions of those signs and
features that that hint even before you
are kind of down the rabbit hole of
having no choice but to act out type of
thing see seeing your so need to do
something palpable is a hindrance
already the pressure to well of course
it's going to you're going to be
pressure but then there's the choosing
of it yeah yeah but first you accept the
pressure well you automatically accept
the pressure when you choose to act out
of those um the sense of Duty or
whatever it's sort of trying to to make
act then by not acting out you're left
with the pressure so what do you do well
that's what you do you endure that
pressure on the right level you don't
give him by Body by speed mentally you
try to disassociate and unfocus from the
thoughts that are trying to get you
focus you know as I said so many times
before already say you're pressured by
um by by ill will okay you're not doing
anything by Body you're not doing
anything by
speech mentally there thoughts revolving
around it but you are the one who then
focuses your lens onto them and that
gives the momentum so it's like and in
the same way when people think I must
stop these thoughts in order to stop
them you need to pick them up first so
either way you focus on them in order to
deal with them you you're hooked you you
stepped into a trap so on the mental
level regardless of the hindrance when
these thoughts are trying to crystallize
themselves into Central thoughts or
thoughts of ill will or thoughts of
restlessness that last part you don't
do that's what words he doesn't welcome
he doesn't Delight he like okay these
thoughts trying to enter it's not my job
no Duty and it's actually going to um
make me fall into a trap if I try to
deal and prevent them or stop them but
it is my job to not allow them to take
that Center Stage off my focus of my
attention so you want to know that they
are there and you already know that they
are there as I said before even before
you allow thoughts to specifically
crystallize in your mind you know
exactly what direction they will be
crystallizing you know exactly what
thoughts would be if it's lust if it's
anger you know EX L where it's going to
go so you don't give that last push on
that mental level and if that pressure
for those thoughts to crystallize stays
there with you for days that's your
training not allowing that last drop of
of crystallization of that focusing on
them but not completely trying to ignore
what's happening well if you're doing it
rightly you won't be able to ignore it
because obviously the knowledge of what
you pressed towards it is there it is
known so you don't try to distract
yourself from it either or let me do
something so I completely forget about
the whole picture no no no let me just
forget about the last the tip of those
thoughts they would kind of give them
that momentum and weight through my own
mental acceptance of them but everything
else I mustn't forget I mustn't forget
that I'm still under the liability of
those of those pressures I mustn't
forget that I'm still under the
liability of lust aversion anxiety cuz
see recognizing liability to a hindrance
it's already a thought it's already a
broader more General more peripheral
sense of Nita and characteristics of
those states of mind even without you
waiting to fully experience anxiety or
lust so now those thoughts are something
you realize oh so now I could train in
regard to them as well those ambiguous
non defined yet fully known in that
sense you know exactly where these these
weird kind of background mood states of
Mind are leaning towards you would if
you stop sit down stop distracting
yourself and say where is this taking me
you would know it's going to be either
lust desire restlessness doubt uh or
just laziness and distraction it's going
to be one of the hindrance hindrance say
so so that's the point in order to start
Discerning these these uh
broader even less clear less defined
less crystallized
nitas you need to first and foremost
stop feeding the current ones
stop grasping the signs and features how
does s to say how does s to say so signs
and features are always that peripheral
in regard to whatever you're attending
and whatever you're preoccupied with
it's where that pressure is it's where
that contact is it's where that whole
kind of Sankar of of that activation
kind of comes from you not seeing them
picking them up you are already under
their under their
momentum so you can't start from there
you can't just stop them on the level of
your mind if your physical behavior is
not purified if your verbal behavior is
not purified but if it were if it was
then okay now this does become a more
palpable ground where you could work
rightly where you could recognize the
pressure of a lust or a ill will feel it
you going obviously feel the pressure
because I said you start in reverse
order you don't start being unpressured
by hindrance you're going to feel the
pressure and then Rec recogniz what
thoughts mind wants to think about and
is kind of thinking here and there but
without your input and then it's like
okay this is still not my problem I
don't have to deal with this because
dealing with this requir me to pick it
up requires me to pick it up all I need
to do is not allow that careless
attending to them they would then
carelessly crystallize them and
carelessly feed them further and give
them even more momentum and if I do
which inevitably you will in the
beginning it's not like okay well now I
have to engage with them even more to
undo what I did mistakenly no at any
given point you catch yourself half an
hour caught in the thoughts you
shouldn't have been allowing the
crystallization and the center stage at
any given point the the the principle of
withdrawal from them is the same there
and then when you become self-aware you
don't allow the Senter stage you don't
allow you unfocus just to the degree
that you were giving them the momentum
that's it so it's not there is at no
point it's Justified to pick a hindrance
up in order to to deal with
it and that's the whole practice of of
yonara done rightly whereby it's not
about what you're attending it's about
seeing through what the Mind wants you
to
attend and then what you are left with
is as the sutta says when the hindrances
present themselves but you see through
them correctly you don't pick the signs
and features you don't fall into the
Trap what you're left with in case of
lust is the signs of beautiful that are
not you have no lust in regard to the
signs of repulsive you have no ill will
in regard
to what was the other one the the things
suitable for
doubt which is which is still not doubt
only when you pick it up when you choose
to act out of that pressure that things
suitable for doubt are putting on
you you you still not hindered yeah the
the tiredness it's like wrongly
attending to the sign of laziness to the
to the Post possibility of not doing
anything yeah dness but in and of itself
that's still not a hindrance the
hindrance is when you uh act out of the
that initial pressure that they put on
you because the mind is not trained in
regard to the pressure and that's then
you start evolving and you think you're
dealing with them but in reality it
makes no difference to Mara as long as
you take them yeah you whether you go
one way or the other way as long as you
first take it that's all he wants you
are still within its his control and the
domain so you just get more and more uh aware
so you just get more and more uh aware
of the
directions that your mind is kind of
sending you towards is pointing towards
but even though it's not in those course
actions uh just that the just the subtle
the the flavor almost tendency
inclination of the mind you could pick
up even though it doesn't seem like just
doing anything yeah well it's
technically yeah exactly technically
it's not doing anything yet
but that doesn't mean that it's not
setting up yeah to do those things and
that's what you need to start
recognizing that again all the simul
about the nimas and secondary
characteristics the Buddha gave in the
sutas were exactly that it's like the
The Cook The skilled cook who doesn't
just give the food to the king and then
forgets where that where that food kind
of led him last
time oh he eats this he doesn't eat it
sometimes he so it's like you want to be
able to foresee so yeah there's no lust
there's no version there's no doubt oh
what do I do well recognize that those
things are absent and then
see while they're absent is your mind
now leaning towards them are you doing
things by Body speech mind carelessly
that's bringing you closer to them CU
that's already the
hindrance because it's going to be
rooted in some sort of compulsion in
some sort of pressure however subtle it
might be and as such it's a hindrance you're
be and as such it's a hindrance you're
already already hindered even on the
level of those possibilities of
Engagement if you are not seeing through
the nature of those
possibilities kind of this image of
having a a a compass the right Compass
you know exactly what direction you
should be going in what direction you
shouldn't be going in like a um maybe
like a captain on a boat you know cuz
just a little bit a degree off yeah it
looks like you're going to to a certain
Island but it's actually a degree of of
course like it's it will be uh it's not
going to be absolutely 100% accurate
from the start it's like through trial
and error and refinement you're getting
a a more accurate and accurate reading
as to like the signs and features you're
becoming even more skilled cook you
recognize three days ahead what the king
will want type of thing where the king's
preferences are heading um so that's
that's kind of the whole the whole point
but as I said it's not like you have to
do something on account of it any
different thing it's the problem is you
not recognizing in the first place and
then doing everything else but the thing
you should do and thing you should do is
abstain from doing anything on account
of picking up the pressure and instead
recognize that whenever there is a
pressure of any hindrance lust aversion
laziness uh restlessness anxiety doubt
Whenever there is a pressure of any
hindrance there is associated thoughts that want
there is associated thoughts that want
to take the center stage of your
attention of your mind want to run the
show and that's what you don't do I
won't give them that last last
satisfaction of mentally okay let me
take this up that's it but see that's
quite a hard thing to do especially in
the beginning where your whole being
depends on doing and managing and
fighting and defending yourself from
these pressures that arise
pressures that arise
but you inadvertently by dealing by
acting out of a pressure you're in
inadvertently affirming it you're
inadvertently picking up what a pressure
is serving you with and then you try to
counter it with with asuba or with meta
or with this and it never
works because you're picking it up but
if you don't pick it up then the asuba
is discerned on the level of that
possibility of the beauty without you
needing to pick it up because beautiful
is already fact
ugly you don't need to pick up the
beautiful to prove to yourself that it's
ugly you just need to not pick it up
stay long enough with it and you'll
discern the ugliness that's exactly what
sud says within the sign of subba he
sees a
subba and if he becomes skilled in that
then he can see it either way within a
subba he can see
subba not at the expense of it not
replacing one with the other just seeing
through he sees the whole extent yeah